<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Vincent's Blog</title><link>https://voostindie.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Vincent's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://voostindie.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>"Doing Knowledge Work" part 1: Introduction to the Series</title><link>https://voostindie.github.io/2021/12/18/knowledge-work-01/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://voostindie.github.io/2021/12/18/knowledge-work-01/</guid><description>Introduction I set up a blog because I enjoy tinkering with one. But now that I have one, what do I put on it? What is it that I&amp;rsquo;m not only willing to share with the world, but that at least some people might find interesting and useful?
For a long while I thought about this. Then it dawned on me. It&amp;rsquo;s obvious: what I&amp;rsquo;m going to write about is personal productivity.</description></item><item><title>How I Manage This Blog</title><link>https://voostindie.github.io/2021/11/25/how-i-manage-this-blog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://voostindie.github.io/2021/11/25/how-i-manage-this-blog/</guid><description>TL;DR Markdown files in a Git repository Static site generation with Hugo Automatic publication to GitHub Pages If these words make you woozy, then this is not for you.
Markdown files in a Git repository Over a decade ago I settled on Markdown for all my writing. Although it has some drawbacks, the benefits easily outweigh them. At least for me. I can view my writing with any text editor, also 30 years from now.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://voostindie.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://voostindie.github.io/about/</guid><description>Arriving Somewhere But Not Here is the title of a track on the 2005 album Deadwing from the band Porcupine Tree. It&amp;rsquo;s 12 minutes long and goes all over the place. I love this track and I love the album!
I like the title as a subtitle for this blog, because it can mean so many things. For example: you, as a casual reader, somehow ended up here, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably not where you planned to be.</description></item></channel></rss>